<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An antidote against the venom of Quakerism, or, Some observations, on a little pamphlet, stiled, The Christianity of the people commonly called Quakers by John Meriton ...</title>
            <author>Meriton, John, 1666-1717.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 79 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50679</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1816</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11247</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12929451</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12929451</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95614</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50679)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95614)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 989:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An antidote against the venom of Quakerism, or, Some observations, on a little pamphlet, stiled, The Christianity of the people commonly called Quakers by John Meriton ...</title>
                  <author>Meriton, John, 1666-1717.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author, and are to be sold by J. Robinson ... and H. Rhodes ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Whitehead, George, 1636?-1723. --  Christianity of the people commonly called Quakers.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:95614:1"/>
            <head>AN ANTIDOTE Againſt the Venom of Quakeriſm.</head>
            <p>BEFORE I enter upon the Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Quakers Principles, as here Profeſſed, and, as I ſuppoſe, Owned by them, I ſhall very briefly deſire the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to take Notice, what is underſtood by the Term <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> or what is neceſſary in a ſtrict and proper Senſe, to Entitle a Man to be a Chriſtian: For the making up then this good Compoſition, it is not enough for a Man to know and acknowledge God as the One only true God, Creator of all things, to Depend upon, and to be Subject to him, to Love him, our Neighbour, and our Selves, to walk Sober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Honeſtly, and to practice all thoſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Duties, which by the Light and Law of Nature, he may be Convinced of; for theſe a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:95614:2"/>
Man may believe, and be conſormable thereto, and yet be no Chriſtian. For who doubts, but that ſome of the Heathens, thus far believed and practiced, who were not only altogether ignorant of Chriſt, but alſo vehemently op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed him, and the Chriſtian Name? (Tho' ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Will. Penn</hi>'s Notion of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, in his <hi>Addreſs to Proteſtants,</hi> p. 119. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Edition, theſe muſt be Chriſtians.) <hi>For what is Chriſt,</hi> ſays he, <hi>but Meekneſs, Juſtice, Mercy, Patience, Charity, and Vertue in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, even the <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves, who were once God's Choſen People, and muſt be Saved thro' Faith in the Meſſiah that was to come cannot, in a ſtrict Senſe, be called Chriſtians their State being no Chriſtian State; however Obedient they might be to the Legal Diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation they lived under, yet they could no from thence be Entituled Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>For to Entitle a Man to be a Chriſtian, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> muſt neceſſarily believe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to be already come; nay, that Partic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> and Numeric<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Man Chriſt Jeſus, who was Born of the Vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary,</hi> and was of the Seed of <hi>Abraha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> according to the Fleſh, to be the Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God, that was promiſed to come in due time that this very Man was Crucified, Died, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Roſe again from the Dead, and is Aſcende<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>&amp;c.—Without Controverſie great is the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtery of Godlineſs, God was Manifeſt in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Fleſh, Juſtified in the Spirit, Believed on the World, Received up into Glory,</hi> 1 Tim. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:95614:2"/>
This Chriſt, God-Man, as come and crucified, was that main Foundation of the Goſpel, and Chriſtianity: Theſe were new Articles, Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon a new Diſpenſation, without the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of which (not to name ſome others, which may be thought by ſome alſo neceſſary, ſuch as Baptiſm by Water, and the Sacrament of the Lord's Supper by Bread and Wine) a Man cannot be called a Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>Many there are indeed who lay Claim to this Holy and Honourable Profeſſion, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Juſt Title, who fiercely contend for the Name, tho' woful ſtrangers to the Nature of Chriſtianity; who ſet up for more Pure and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined Chriſtians, than are to be found in other Societies, tho' they have ſcarcely any better Title to this Name, than their being Born in a Chriſtian Nation. And thus the Quakers im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and put upon the World; they ſet up for the great Modellers and Refiners of Religion, and Condemn all others as full of Filth and Dreggs, whenas they themſelves, as deceitful Workers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> themſelves into the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles of Chriſt, cannot be looked upon any otherwiſe, at beſt, than good Moral Heathens; and many of them ſhort of that. Indeed, could we take them at their word, or would they take words in their common Acceptation, it muſt be granted then, that their Profeſſion, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the greateſt part of this Pamphlet, as well as ſome others, (<hi>viz. Will. Penn</hi>'s <hi>Key, Crook</hi>'s <hi>Principles,</hi> &amp;c.) would ſeem Orthodox, but
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:95614:3"/>
this they will not do; no, you muſt Conſtrue them by their Intentions; for, ſays <hi>George Whitehead</hi> in his <hi>Counterfeit Convert,</hi> p. 72. <hi>I may ſee cauſe otherwiſe to word the Matter, and yet our Intentions be the ſame:</hi> You may then ſee Juſt Cauſe to miſtruſt them in theſe their ſeeming Orthodox Confeſſions. They have a Nauſeous Pill to give you; but that it may not be Diſtaſteful and Loathſom to the Palate, they Gild it over, (as the Writers for Popery in the Late K. <hi>J</hi>'s Reign, the other Day, did) to make it the more Glib and Eaſie to a Proteſtant Guſt, and Swallow; they are Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters at the Art of Painting, uſing feigned words, and fair Speeches, which was the old way of deceiving the Hearts of the Simple; by which means, many Poor, Unthinking, and Well-meaning People, are now Enſnared and Involved in the ſame Errors with themſelves: By theſe, and the like plauſible Profeſſions, and ſmooth Pretences, have they endeavoured to inſinuate into, and impoſe upon, our Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours; who, no doubt, can eaſily diſcern (how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Artificially Gilded and Varniſhed) their Blaſphemous Opinions, relating to Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as well as to our Government. And to this end and purpoſe, in the Month of <hi>March</hi> laſt paſt, there were Two Books preſented to Both Houſes of Parliament; the one Entituled, <hi>A Brief Diſcovery of ſome of the Blaſphemous and Seditious Principles,</hi> &amp;c. The other En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, <hi>Some few of the</hi> Quakers <hi>many Horrid</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:95614:3"/>
               <hi>Blaſphemies, Hereſies,</hi> &amp;c. And alſo a Sheet, Entituled, <hi>Some Reaſons humbly Offered,—Why the</hi> Quakers <hi>ſhould be Examined.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to proceed to an Examination of their Pamphlet in its ſeveral Parts.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What is your Belief concerning the Bleſſed Trinity, as our Term is?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Our Belief is, That in the Unity of the Godhead, there is Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, theſe Three Divine Witneſſes, that bear Record in Heaven, the Father, the Word, and the H. Spirit, and that theſe Three are One, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Holy Scripture Teſtimony.</p>
            <p>OBSERVATION.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Note,</hi> It is ſaid of the Oracles of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, that they were made to look with Two Faces, that they might the better effect their Deceits; and agreeable hereto, whatever was delivered by them, was ſpoken in ſuch Dubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Equivocal Terms, as that it ſhould ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way tend to the Satisfaction of the Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee: Juſt ſo do the Quakers now (it being ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to ſerve a preſent Turn) give out a very cunning and plauſible Profeſſion, but in ſuch Dubious Terms, as may look like Good, and Orthodox, and yet be in a great Meaſure Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concileable to their Ancient Friends Principles, and Teſtimonies. It is well known, that the moſt Virulent Poiſon may be Gilded over, and that Varniſh and Paint may be laid on the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95614:4"/>
Fouleſt Cauſe; and conſequently, the Quakers may be guilty of the groſſeſt Errors, under the Mask of Innocence and Zeal, Religion and Purity.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall not trouble the Reader with their Intentions and Meanings, nor Trace them into all their Equivocal Reſerves, (wherein they may be thought to exceed their Brethren the Jeſuites) but rather have recourſe to their own Books, which can't but be allowed to be the beſt, and only way, to know and underſtand their real Principles, as well as Meanings, they being moſt, if not all, pretended to be Wrote from the Mouth of the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> They pretend to make the World be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that they own the Bleſſed Trinity; that is, they pretend to acknowledge a Three, but deny a Trinity, which is to confeſs the ſame thing in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and deny it in <hi>Latine, Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitas</hi> being only <hi>Latine</hi> for the Three; they Profeſs to Believe in the Holy Three, or Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, of Father, Word, and Spirit, as <hi>Penn</hi> tells you in his <hi>Key,</hi> p. 15. but not as Three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: But if not Three Perſons, What Three are they?</p>
            <p>But for your ſatisfaction, give Ear to the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients in their Miniſtry; to that end, hear what their Great and Firſt Apoſtle <hi>George</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſays in his <hi>Great Myſtery,</hi> p. 246. who earneſtly oppoſed his Adverſary, one <hi>Chriſtopher Wade,</hi> for affirming, That the Holy Ghoſt was a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and that there was a Trinity of Three
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:95614:4"/>
Perſons before Chriſt was Born: <hi>The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>doth not tell People of a Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, nor Three Perſons, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t the Common-Prayer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Maſs-Book, ſpeaks of Three Perſons, brought in by thy Father the Pope.</hi> And <hi>Will. Penn</hi> tells us in his <hi>Sandy Foundation,</hi> p. 13. Printed 1668. <hi>That if we pretend to Credit the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, we muſt neceſſarily Conclude our kind of Trinity a Fiction.</hi> And leſt the Reader ſhould not be ſatisfied with his Scripture Proofs and Interpretations, he labours hard to refute it from right Reaſon, (ſo called by him) as in <hi>p.</hi> 13, 14. to give you a Taſte of them: <hi>The Divine Perſons are either Finite, or Infinite; if the firſt, then ſomething Finite is inſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Infinite Subſtance, whereby ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing Finite is in God: If the laſt, then Three diſtinct Infinites, Three Omnipotents, Three Eternals, and ſo Three Gods.</hi> Secondly, <hi>If each Perſon be God, and that God Subſiſts in Three Perſons, then in each Perſon are Three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, or Gods, and from Three they will In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe to Nine, and ſo</hi> ad Infinitum, &amp;c. Again, in <hi>p.</hi> 32. he tells us, That our Trinity (or our imagined Trinity, as he Terms it in <hi>p.</hi> 16.) has not ſo much as a Foundation in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, it being but Man's Invention and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it hath occaſioned Idolatry. See further, <hi>George <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>itehead,</hi> and Three other Quakers, in their Book, Entituled, <hi>Iſhmael and his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther caſt out,</hi> p. 10. where is this Paſſage, <hi>He</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> Mr. <hi>Townſend</hi> a Miniſter in <hi>Norwich,</hi> againſt whom they Diſputed) <hi>is ſhut up with</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:95614:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:95614:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:95614:6"/>
               <hi>the Three Perſons in perpetual Darkneſs, for the Lake and the Pit.</hi> I ſhall add here nothing by way of Inference, but leave it to the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to judge, whether they own the Trinity; being <hi>Thoſe Three Divine Witneſſes, that bear Record in Heaven, the Father, the Word, and the Holy Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what Heaven is that which the <hi>Quakers</hi> mean; not the Glorious Heaven above, but it is the Heaven within thee, where theſe Three Divine Witneſſes are; for ſays <hi>Geo. Fox</hi> in his <hi>Gr. Myſt.</hi> p. 214. <hi>There is none have a Glory and a Heaven, but within them.</hi> Again, ſee his Trial at <hi>Lancaſter</hi> Aſſize, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 21. <hi>I was moved to Pray, and the Thundering Voice an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, I have glorified thee, and will glorifie thee again; and I was filled ſo full of Glory, that my Head and my Ears was filled full of it.</hi> Mark, Reader, here was Thunder within, Glory within, yea, full of Glory; <hi>aurum tenus,</hi> up to the Ears. And ſays <hi>W. Penn</hi> in his <hi>Rejoinder,</hi> p. 179. <hi>To deny the Locality of Heaven, is not very offenſive; and that it looks too Carnal, and indeed</hi> Mahometaniſm, <hi>viz. to aſſert it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, Reader, let this ſerve to Conſtrue their meaning in their Pamphlet, when they ſpeak of Three Divine Witneſſes bearing Record in Heaven; that is to ſay, the Heaven within them.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Do you believe the Divinity and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity of Jeſus Chriſt, the Eternal Son of God; or that Jeſus Chriſt is truly God and Man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:95614:6"/>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes, we verily Believe that Jeſus Chriſt is truly God and Man, according as Holy Scripture Teſtifie of him, <hi>viz.</hi> God over all, Bleſſed for Ever, the True God, and Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life, the One Mediator between God and Man, even the Man Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p>OBSERVATION.</p>
            <p>Now let us ſee whether they believe as they ſay, or whether it be only Paint, or Varniſh, to deceive the Hearts of the Simple.</p>
            <p>To that end, ſee <hi>Geo. Whitehead</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>s <hi>Nature of Chriſtianity,</hi> p. 41. where he thus ſpeaks, <hi>That Chriſt Exiſteth outwardly, Bodily, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out us, at God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>s Right Hand: What Scripture proof hath he for theſe Words?</hi> See alſo his <hi>Truth Defending the</hi> Quakers, <hi>p.</hi> 22. where he affirms, <hi>Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>s coming in the Fleſh, to be but a Figure or Example:</hi> Which is alſo the ſaying of <hi>R. Hubbertborn,</hi> and Juſtified by <hi>G. Whitehead</hi> in his <hi>Judgment Fixed,</hi> p. 336. who tells you plainly what Man Chriſt the <hi>Quakers</hi> own, <hi>i. e.</hi> their Light within only: His words are theſe, <hi>Therefore the Man Chriſt Jeſus was before he came in the Body or Fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Chriſtopher Atkinſon</hi> in his Book cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>The Sward of the Lord drawn,</hi> which was written (as he pretended) from the Mouth of the Lord; and this I cannot omit quoting, for tho his Perſon was diſowned and denied (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he was Hanged for Felony) by ſome of the <hi>Quakers</hi> at <hi>Weſt-Dereham</hi> Church, at the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, yet I never heard it before: No; he
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:95614:7"/>
was a good Man then, and Inſpired, however fallible afterwards; and therefore thoſe his Writings muſt be Valuable and Venerable; and that they are by them ſo accounted, is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent from matter of fact; for when the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers were preſſed by a Clergyman, and others there preſent, at the Second Day Conference, to reject and diſown his Writings under their Hands, they would not be brought to ſuch a reaſonable compliance. I muſt therefore beg leave to inſiſt upon this Book, where in <hi>p.</hi> 5. he hath theſe words, <hi>Your imagined God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Stars, and your Carnal Chriſt, is ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly denied, and teſtified againſt by the Light:—And that this Chriſt is God and Man in one Perſon, it is a Lie.</hi> And again, <hi>Becauſe,</hi> as <hi>Will. Penn</hi> ſays, <hi>it is not reaſonable that a Body of Men ſhould be Concluded by the Word or Act of any one Member,</hi> vid. his <hi>Brief An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to a falſe and fooliſh Libel,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 25. Printed 1678. I ſhall therefore add One or Two more; to that end, ſee G. <hi>Fox Gr. Myſt. p.</hi> 206. <hi>If there be any other Chriſt, but he that was Crucified within, he is the falſe Chriſt:</hi> And ſays <hi>Smith</hi> in his <hi>Primer,</hi> p. 8. Printed 1668. <hi>They that are falſe</hi> (Miniſters) <hi>preach Chriſt without, and bid people believe in him, as he is in Heaven above; but they that are true Miniſters, they preach Chriſt within, and direct People to wait to feel him in themſelves:</hi> And in <hi>p.</hi> 9. he affirms, <hi>That theſe have no more fellowſhip than the Eaſt hath with the Weſt:</hi> Nay <hi>Will. Penn</hi> in his <hi>Addreſs to Proteſtants,</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:95614:7"/>
p. 119. makes Chriſt nothing but <hi>Meekneſs, Juſtice, Patience, Charity, and Vertue in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection:</hi> In ſhort, nothing but an Holy Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, as he elſewhere hath it.</p>
            <p>Now whether theſe Quotations do not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to a plain denial of the Humanity of Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> let the Reader Judge; whatever in this Pamphlet, or in <hi>Will. Penn</hi>'s <hi>Key,</hi> is pretended to the contrary: But yet once more, to corro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borate all I have ſaid on this Head, (as well as to ſhew you how inconſiſtent <hi>Will. Penn</hi> is with himſelf) ſee his <hi>Serious Apology,</hi> p. 146. <hi>That the outward Perſon which Suffered</hi> (at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>) <hi>was properly the Son of God, we utterly deny.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Do you believe and expect Salvation, and Juſtification, by the Righteouſneſs and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of Jeſus Chriſt, or by your own Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Works?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> By Jeſus Chriſt his Righteouſneſs, Merits and Works: God is not indebted to us, for our Deſervings; but we to him, for his Free Grace in Chriſt Jeſus, whereby we are Saved, thro' Faith in him, (not of our ſelves) and by his Grace enabled truly and acceptably to Serve and Follow him; he is our All in All, who works all in us that is well-pleaſing to God.</p>
            <p>OBSERVATION.</p>
            <p>Now to unfold their meaning herein, as is ſaid before, let us hear what their Approved Authors ſay: I ſhall begin with <hi>Geo. White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head,</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:95614:8"/>
who in his <hi>Light and Life,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 16, blames us for laying ſo much ſtreſs upon the ſhedding of Chriſt's Blood, <hi>p.</hi> 38. <hi>The Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> (ſays he) <hi>ſee no need of directing Men to Jeſus Chriſt, or his Blood, as it was outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhed at</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>for Juſtification,</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>p.</hi> 55. <hi>Where doth the Scripture ſay, that the ſhedding of Chriſt 's Blood outwardly was the Meritorious Cauſe of</hi> (Man's) <hi>Salvation.</hi> And in <hi>p.</hi> 64. <hi>It is falſe Doctrine to lay the Meritorious Cauſe or Streſs of Juſtification, upon the ſhedding of that Blood let out by the Spear:</hi> And ſays <hi>Will. Penn</hi> (in Conjunction with his Brother <hi>Whitehead</hi>) in his <hi>Serious Apology,</hi> p. 148. <hi>This indeed we deny,</hi> viz. <hi>Juſtification by the Righteouſneſs which Chriſt hath fulfilled in his own Perſon for us,</hi> (<hi>wholly without us:</hi>)—<hi>And boldly affirm it, in the Name of the Lord, to be the Doctrine of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, and an Arm of the Sea of Corruption, which does now Deluge the whole World.</hi> And ſays <hi>Geo. Whitehead</hi> in his <hi>Counterfeit Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert,</hi> p. 17. 18. Printed 1694. That <hi>it is the Light and Life within, in which is the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate and efficient Cauſe of Man's Salvation; and as for the Sufferings and Death of Chriſt in the Freſh, they do but inſtrumentally Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute thereunto.</hi> And agreeable hereunto, ſee <hi>Iſaac Pennington</hi>'s <hi>Queſtions to Profeſſors,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 25. where there is this Queſtion put, <hi>Can outward Blood cleanſe the Conſcience?</hi> &amp;c. Which, tho' by way of Interrogation, is a very plain and manifeſt denial of the efficacy
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:95614:8"/>
of the Blood of Chriſt, ſhed upon the Croſs for Man's Salvation. Again, <hi>Thomas Lawſon,</hi> a thorow-pac'd <hi>Quaker,</hi> in his <hi>Untaught Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> p. 4. Printed 1655. tells you, <hi>That you muſt not look for Salvation from any Means without:</hi> For when his Opponent had urged, that the Means that leads to Salvation, is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Man, he anſwers, <hi>For all thy Profeſſion, thou art got no further than the Pope, who talk of a Chriſt without, Means of Salvation without, as thou doſt,</hi> p. 5. <hi>Thou art a Fooliſh Builder, ſeeking a Way to Salvation without thee.</hi> If this be not the Myſtery of Iniquity, I know not what may be called ſo. When you have thus compared them, then, <hi>Reader,</hi> judge of the Sincerity of their Profeſſion; for as they thus undervalue the Righteouſneſs and Merits of Jeſus Chriſt, purchaſing Salvation for us, ſo do they ſet up, extol and magnifie their own Righteouſneſs and Works, like to their Brethren in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as will be made appear in the next Obſervation; only in this, they exceed all the Meritorious Boaſts of thoſe their Kindred, in affirming, that their Sufferings are Greater, and more Unjuſt, than the Sufferings in the Days of Chriſt, His Apoſtles and Martyrs. See <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough</hi>'s <hi>Works,</hi> p. 273.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Do you believe Remiſſion of Sin, and Redemption thro' the Sufferings, Death, and Blood of Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:95614:9"/>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes, thro' Faith in Him, as He ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd and died for all Men, and gave Himſelf a Ranſom for all, and his Blood being ſhed for the Remiſſion of Sins, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>OBSERVATION.</p>
            <p>Here their Profeſſion ſeems to be very Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox; but obſerve, if we will give Credit to their Ancient and Approved Authors, (who pretended they wrote from the Mouth of the Lord;) it is ſtill but Paint and Deceit; for Remiſſion of Sins, or Redemption thro' the Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, or Righteouſneſs of another, is not by them believed. See the Works of their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, and Son of Thunder and Conſolation, <hi>Edw. Burroughs,</hi> p. 33. <hi>God doth not accept a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, where there is any Failing, or who do not fulfil the Law, and anſwer every Demand of Juſtice.</hi> This, Reader, were there no other Inſtance, confutes their Plauſible Pretence to Juſtification, and Remiſſion of Sin, by the Righteouſneſs and Merits of Chriſt. But for your further Satisfaction, ſee <hi>W. Penn</hi>'s <hi>Sandy Foundation,</hi> p. 25. <hi>Juſtification of Perſons is not from the Imputation of another's Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but from the Actual Performing and Keeping God's Righteous Statutes.</hi> Again, ſee his <hi>Serious Apol.</hi> p. 148. <hi>Juſtification by the Righteouſneſs of another, or which is ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled for us in his own Perſon, we boldly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, in the Name of the Lord, to be the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Devils, and an Arm of the Sea of Corruption, which does now deluge the whole</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:95614:9"/>
               <hi>World.</hi> Again, once more ſee his <hi>Sandy Found.</hi> p. 25, 30. <hi>It is a great Abomination to ſay—That he (Chriſt) having ſatisfied for our Sins, we may be Juſtified by the Imputation of his perfect Righteouſneſs;</hi> and yet they tell you in this Pamphlet, <hi>That he Died for our Sins, and Roſe again for our Juſtification,</hi> when as <hi>ib. p.</hi> 31. <hi>W. Penn</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of ſuch a Doctrine,</hi> (i. e. Imputative Righteouſneſs) <hi>is both Irreligious and Irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional.</hi> Again, in his <hi>Serious Apol.</hi> p. 148. he tells you, <hi>That Death came by Actual Sin, not Imputative, therefore Juſtification unto Life came by Actual Righteouſneſs, not Imputative.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here, <hi>Reader,</hi> as <hi>G. Keith</hi> has well obſerv'd, in his Abſtract, you may obſerve how far this contradicts his late Doctrine of Juſtification, in his Primitive Chriſtianity, and late Creeds.</p>
            <p>And why indeed ſhould they believe Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Sins, and Redemption thro' Chriſt's Sufferings, and Juſtification by his Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, when as they believe themſelves to be Perfect, as God, and Free from Sin. <hi>Firſt,</hi> Perfect as God, ſee <hi>G. Fox</hi>'s <hi>Great Myſtery,</hi> p. 282. One ſaid, Surely they cannot be Perfect here, or hereafter, in Equality, but only in Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; <hi>Fox</hi> anſwers, <hi>Chriſt makes no Diſtinction in his Words, but ſaith, Be ye Perfect, even as your Heavenly Father is Perfect; and as He is, ſo are We; and that which is Perfect, as He is Perfect, is in Equality with the ſame thing, which is of God, and from God.</hi> 2<hi>dly,</hi> They profeſs to be free from Sin, as you may
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:95614:10"/>
ſee in <hi>G. Fox</hi>'s <hi>Great Myſt.</hi> p. 101. <hi>It is the Doctrine of Devils, that preacheth, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall have Sin, and be in a Warfare ſo long <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> they be on Earth.</hi> And p. 231. he ſays, <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> who come to Chriſt, the Second</hi> Adam, <hi>they come to Perfection in the Life of God, out of the Firſt</hi> Adam; p. 271. <hi>For who are Sanctified have perfect Unity, perfect Knowledge, perfect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> And <hi>Will. Penn,</hi> in his <hi>Truth Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d,</hi> &amp;c. as the Authors of a Book, Entituled, <hi>A brief Diſcovery,</hi> &amp;c. takes notice) laughs at the Church of <hi>England.</hi> for confeſſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Sinners, or praying to God for Mercy. <hi>Alas! poor Souls,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Penn</hi>) <hi>are not you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Mercy upon us, miſerable Sinners, there is no Health in us, from Seven to Seven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty?</hi> This Doctrine of Sinleſs Perfection being the approved Doctrine of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and that in Oppoſition to all Profeſſors of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith, there is no Reaſon why they ſhould believe Remiſſion of Sin, Redemption, and Juſtification by the Righteouſneſs and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of Jeſus Chriſt; becauſe they themſelves pretend to be Perfect as God, yea, as Perfect and Free from Sin.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Do you believe and own the Divine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of Jeſus Chriſt in his Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes verily, we ſincerely believe—and own Chriſt; not only as He is the Light of the World, enlightning every Man coming into i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, but alſo that he is given for a Leader, and for a Commander, and that He is both King,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:95614:10"/>
Prieſt and Prophet to and over His Church and People, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>OBSERVATION.</p>
            <p>This Profeſſion of theirs, if Sincere, would indeed comprehend a great Part of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion; but if the above Quotations be true, they will give you juſt Cauſe to ſuſpect them, even in this. Obſerve then how they believe the Kingly Office of Chriſt: For that, examine, whether they do not attribute that to <hi>G. Fox,</hi> their firſt Apoſtle, which is due to Chriſt Himſelf alone? See <hi>Tyranny and Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie detected.</hi> p. 19. where <hi>Solomon Eccles</hi> thus celebrates <hi>G. Fox,</hi> viz. <hi>Bleſſed be the Man that came out of the North, bleſſed be the Womb that bear him, and the Breaſt that gave him Suck.</hi> And <hi>ib.</hi> ſee there a Letter, written by <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Coale,</hi> a Quaker, from <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> to <hi>G. Fox,</hi> 24. Day, 12 Month, 1658. which is ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by <hi>W. Penn,</hi> in his <hi>Judas and the Jews,</hi> p. 44. 45, 46. viz.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dear</hi> G. Fox, <hi>who art the Father of many Nations, whoſe Life hath reached thro' us thy Children, even to the Iſles afar off, to the beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of many again to a lively Hope, for which Generations to come ſhall call thee Bleſſed; whoſe Being and Habitation is in the Power of the Higheſt, in which thou rule? and governeſt in Righteouſneſs, and thy Kingdom is eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e, and the Encreaſe thereof is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end.</hi> Now by theſe Expreſſions, as <hi>Edw. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ye</hi> in his <hi>Antichriſt in Spirit Unmasked,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:95614:11"/>
well obſerves, whether the Scepter be not wreſted out of Chriſt's Hand, and given to <hi>G. Fox,</hi> let the <hi>Reader</hi> judge, by conſidering the ſeveral Parts of it. 1<hi>ſt,</hi> Then obſerve, he doth expreſly aſcribe to him a Kingdom; <hi>Thy Kingdom,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and thou Ruleſt and Governeſt;</hi> muſt not then ſuch a one be an Actual King? 2<hi>dly,</hi> He deſcribes the Subjects of this Kingdom; who thoſe are, you may, with ſome Aſſurance, venture to gueſs, <hi>viz. Joſiah Coale,</hi> and the reſt of the Ancient Society of <hi>Quakers,</hi> to whom the Life of <hi>G. Fox</hi> hath reached thro' ſuch Illuſtrious Children, even <hi>to the Iſles afar off, to the begetting them again to a lively Hope;</hi> and theſe are great in Numbers, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he calls him <hi>the Father of many Nations.</hi> 3<hi>dly,</hi> As Mr. <hi>Paye</hi> ſays, he tells us what kind of Power and Authority it is, in which this King Rules and Governs, namely, <hi>In the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Higheſt;</hi> viz. a Spiritual and Divine Power, not like that of the Kingdoms of Men. 4<hi>thly,</hi> You have here the Stability of this Kingdom, <hi>Thy Kingdom is eſtabliſhed in Peace.</hi> 5<hi>thly,</hi> You have the Extent of this Kingdom alſo; namely, <hi>The Encreaſe thereof is without end;</hi> it is a Boundleſs Kingdom. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Take notice of the Excellency of this Kingdom, which is ſuch, (and <hi>Fox,</hi> this King's Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſo great) that not only the preſent Age, but <hi>Generations to come ſhall call him Bleſſed.</hi> From hence judge, if <hi>G. Fox</hi> is not Inveſted and Throned in Chriſt's Kingly Office. They have then no Reaſon to take it ill, if we call <hi>G. Fox</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:95614:11"/>
the King of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> ſince it plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears from the Teſtimony of <hi>Joſiah Coale,</hi> (an Eminent Teacher of theirs) and vindicated, as above quoted, by <hi>Will. Penn,</hi> and approved of by their Second Day Meeting, that he is ſo, even as Chriſt is King of the Chriſtians; but poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly it may be objected, That it is Chriſt in <hi>G. Fox</hi> that hath this Regal or Kingly Power, (as <hi>G. Whitehead</hi> aſſerts in his <hi>Innocency againſt Envy,</hi> p. 18.) we might have then reaſonably expected, that it would have been ſo expreſſed; Meanings are not to be underſtood, but by Words; and as for Words, none can be plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and more expreſſive, which <hi>W. Penn</hi> affirms to be no Blaſphemy, but harmleſs and Innocent. See further, <hi>Tyranny and Hypocriſie detected,</hi> p. 45. as alſo <hi>Judas and the Jews,</hi> p. 85. where you have this Saying of King <hi>George</hi> repeated, <hi>Friends, altho' I have not told it you, I do now declare it, I have Power to bind and to looſe whom I pleaſe.</hi> And who can deny it, ſince he hath deprived Chriſt of His Kingly Office, and aſſumed it to Himſelf? But I do ſtill expect the <hi>Quakers</hi> will ſay, as <hi>G. Whitehead</hi> in his <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency againſt Envy,</hi> p. 18. plainly intimates, it is not <hi>G. Fox, but the Light, or Chriſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in him,</hi> that Aſſumes this Kingly Power; but it will then follow, that every <hi>Quaker</hi> is a King, becauſe every <hi>Quaker</hi> has the Light within; which Light muſt be obeyed, <hi>ſince all Power in Heaven and Earth is committed to it.</hi> See <hi>Smith</hi>'s <hi>Primer,</hi> p. 13. alſo <hi>Joſiah Coale</hi>'s <hi>Works,</hi> p. 93. See <hi>G. Fox,</hi> Jun. p. 50. whom you
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:95614:12"/>
may obſerve to ſpeak plain and home to the Point, <hi>viz. I the Light will fall upon you, and grinde you to Pouder. All—who will not own me the Light in you; And—I will make you know, that I the Light am the true Eternal God, which created all things; and that by me, the Light, all things are upheld, and that there is not another beſides me that can ſave.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, <hi>Reader,</hi> compare theſe Quotations with this their late Profeſſion, now under Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, and then judge whether the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> do really own the Kingly Office of Chriſt. For whereas they pretend to be obedient to the Laws of Chriſt our Lord, and His Ordinances, are they not, both by their Doctrine and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices, made Void, Contemned, and Rejected, as will further hereafter appear. But to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed.</p>
            <p>2<hi>dly,</hi> Let us now ſee how they own Chriſt's Prieſtly Office. For who (as above) can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that they really own the Prieſtly Office of Chriſt, when they deny his Humanity, as owned by all Orthodox Chriſtians? To which I ſhall add theſe Reaſons, with ſome little Mixture of Matter of Fact, to let the <hi>Reader</hi> ſee, that notwithſtanding their Plauſible Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, they muſt be thought to deny the Prieſtly Office of Chriſt. For,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> If they deny the Perſon or Humanity of Chriſt, (as above ſhewed) they cannot own Chriſt's Prieſtly Office; tho' the Scripture tells us of one Mediator betwixt God and Man, the Man Chriſt Jeſus, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 5. the <hi>Quakers</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:95614:12"/>
tell you, that Chriſt was never ſeen with Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Eyes, nor heard with Carnal Ears. <hi>Wool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich</hi>'s <hi>Declaration to the Baptiſts,</hi> p. 13. But did not the <hi>Jews</hi> that Crucified him, ſee him? Yes, no doubt, they did: What then is their Meaning? Why, their Meaning is, that was not Chriſt that the <hi>Jews</hi> Saw and Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, that was but the Outward Garment, which the <hi>Quakers</hi> can never call Chriſt. See <hi>Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nington</hi>'s <hi>Queſtion to Profeſſors,</hi> p. 33. As a Confirmation of this they teach, <hi>That Chriſt hath no Body but his Church.</hi> See <hi>Joſiah Coale</hi>'s <hi>Works,</hi> p. 332. It appears then from hence, that they deny the Mediator, the Man Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p>Nay, further, if they deny the Blood of the Sacrifice, which Chriſt our High Prieſt offered upon the Croſs, it muſt then be granted, that they deny the Prieſtly Office of Chriſt; and that they do ſcornfully Contemn the Blood of Chriſt, I have already ſhown; how then can they own Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>s Prieſtly Office? Neither indeed, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Principles, is it at all requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite, they ſhould own this, or ſtand in need of a Mediator; for if they are Perfect, as ſee <hi>G. Fox</hi>'s <hi>Great Myſtery,</hi> p. 282. and without Sin. <hi>ib.</hi> 101, and 231. and are come to the end of Faith, as <hi>Lawſon</hi> ſays in his <hi>Untaught Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> p. 10. and if <hi>Edw. Burrough</hi> in his Works ſays true, <hi>p.</hi> 33. <hi>That God doth not accept any, where there is any Failing, or who do not fulfil the Law, and anſwer every Demand of Juſtice;</hi> and if <hi>Will. Penn</hi>'s Aſſertion be true, <hi>That</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:95614:13"/>
               <hi>Juſtification is from the Actual performing and keeping God's Righteous Statutes,</hi> ſee his <hi>Sandy Foundation,</hi> p. 25. then what need have they of the Mediatory Office of Chriſt? Without any further Enlargement, this may ſuffice, to ſatisfie any Impartial <hi>Reader,</hi> that the <hi>Quakers</hi> do not own the Prieſtly Office of Chriſt. But then,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Do they own his Prophetick Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice? <hi>Yes verily,</hi> (ſays the <hi>Quakers</hi>) <hi>we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and own him to be Prophet to and over his Church and People, and we are to hear him in all things.</hi> But pray obſerve, how can this be, when they ſo plainly deny His Humane Body, as above ſhewed? The Scripture in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed tell us, That we are obliged to hear this Prophet, Chriſt ſpeaking to us, as in <hi>Acts</hi> 3. 23. Him ſhall ye hear in all things, whatſoever He ſhall ſay unto you: And it ſhall come to paſs, that every Soul which will not hear that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, ſhall be deſtroyed from among the People. This is He that God the Father from Heaven teſtified of, <hi>Mat.</hi> 17. 5. ſaying, <hi>This is my Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Son, hear ye him.</hi> And the <hi>Quakers</hi> ſeem to join iſſue with us in this Matter, ſaying in their Pamphlet, <hi>p.</hi> 6. We are to hear him in all things; but notwithſtanding this Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they neither do nor will hear Him; no; their Chriſt within, (which is that which they are obliged to give ear to) tells them other things than our Outward Chriſt or Prophet does. For Inſtance, our Prophet Chriſt fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently preached from the Scriptures, <hi>Matth.</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:95614:13"/>
21. 42. For ſaith he, <hi>Did ye never read in the Scriptures, the Stone that was ſet at nought by you Builders, the ſame is become the Head of the Corner.</hi> Matth 22. 19. <hi>Ye do err, not knowing the Scriptures.</hi> John 5. 39. <hi>Search the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> &amp;c. And what was more frequent, than for our Lord Chriſt to preach from the Scriptures, and to convince his Adverſaries by them? But the <hi>Quakers</hi> reject this Way. For when one <hi>Matthew Caffyn</hi> had affirmed, That the Scripture was the Touchſtone to try Spirits withal; <hi>Lawſon</hi>'s <hi>Untaught Teacher,</hi> p. 14. his Anſwer was this, <hi>That is another Lie; the Scripture is not the Trier of Spirits.</hi> And whereas <hi>Matthew Caffyn</hi> affirm'd, <hi>ibid.</hi> p. 15. <hi>That the Law without Man is that which convinces Man of Sin:</hi> He anſwers, <hi>That is another Lie.</hi> See <hi>Saul</hi>'s <hi>Errand to</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcus, <hi>p.</hi> 7. Where you may find, that it was objected to the <hi>Quakers,</hi> that they had ſaid, <hi>Whoever took a Place of Scripture, and made a Sermon of it, or from it, was a Conjurer, and his Preaching was Conjuration.</hi> To which <hi>G. Fox</hi> anſwered, <hi>All that do ſtudy to raiſe a Living Thing out of a Dead, to raiſe the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit out of the Letter, are Conjurers; and their Teaching is from Conjuration, which is not ſpoken from the Mouth of the Lord.</hi> Thus do the <hi>Quakers</hi> oppoſe the Teachings of Chriſt's Prophetick Office. And further, that the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> deny the Prophetick Office of Chriſt is even demonſtrable, by their denying his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel Ordinances, which leads me to the Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:95614:14"/>
of the next Head in their Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet, <hi>p.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Do yo believe or own Baptiſm, as eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential to Chriſtianity, or neceſſary to Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and for the Ingrafting us into Chriſt and His Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> We believe, and are fully perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that Baptiſm, which is eſſential to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, and the ſaving Baptiſm, or the Cauſe without which, none can be true Chriſtians, or ſaved, is the Inward or Spiritual Waſhing of Regeneration by the Word of Life. This is the Saving Baptiſm into Chriſt and His Church, which produceth the Anſwer of a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience towards God, of which the Outward was a Figure, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 21. This is that one Baptiſm of Chriſt, by one Spirit, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that one Body, whereof Chriſt is Head; and for Dipping or Sprinkling Infants, or young Children, we find no Precept or Precedent, in Holy Scripture, for the Practice thereof, and <hi>Ergo,</hi> we cannot think our not believing it eſſential or neceſſary to Salvation, or making Chriſtians, a ſufficient Argument to prove us no Chriſtians, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 6, 7.</p>
            <p>OBSERVATION.</p>
            <p>By this their Anſwer, they do not Inſinuate to, but plainly tell the World, what Baptiſm it is that is eſſentially neceſſary to Salvation, or making Chriſtians; that is, the Inward or Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Waſhing of Regeneration by the Word
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:95614:14"/>
of Life; the Waſhing or Cleanſing of the Heart, or an Inward Converſion to God; by this their Confeſſion, it is evident enough, that they make void and aboliſh the Sacred Ordinance of the Outward Baptiſm by Water. Whether Infants are to partake of this Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Ordinance, is not my Buſineſs here to prove; but whether Outward Baptiſm by Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is the Sacred Ordinance of Chriſt, as neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to be believ'd, and ſaving; or Inward Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Waſhing or Cleanſing of the Heart; or an Inward Converſion to God: Let them firſt own the Outward Baptiſm by Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as our Saviour's Baptiſm, then they may expect a Proof of our Practice, in admitting Infants to be made Partakers of this Ordinance; but this they utterly reject, and diſown; and for the Proof of it, obſerve, that we have Chriſt's own Command, his own Example, and the Practice of the Apoſtles for it; the Words of our Saviour, by way of a Command to His Apoſtles, are plain, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. 19. <hi>Go and teach all Nations;</hi> or as the Original has it, <hi>Go and diſciple all Nations, Baptizing,</hi> or Waſhing them (which is the proper Engliſh for Baptizing) <hi>in the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> The <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> indeed, to enervate and make void this Command, will tell you, that this Place is to be taken Figuratively, and meant of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Baptiſm; the Waſhing or Cleanſing of the Heart; or that of the Holy Ghoſt; but that it is to be taken Literally, and meant of the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:95614:15"/>
Outward Baptiſm by Water, you may diſcern from our Saviour's Example, <hi>Mark</hi> 9. 10. and from His Practice, as you may read in the 3d of St. <hi>John, v.</hi> 26. <hi>They came unto</hi> John, <hi>and ſaid unto him,</hi> Rabbi; <hi>he that was with thee beyond</hi> Jordan, <hi>to whom thou beareſt witneſs, behold the ſame Baptiseth, and all Men come to him.</hi> That this was Water Baptiſm, cannot be doubted, becauſe the Inward Baptiſm of the Holy Ghoſt was not yet given; no, not till 50 Days after the Reſurrection. See the 2d of the <hi>Acts,</hi> and the 3d of St. <hi>John,</hi> v. 22. <hi>Jeſus came, and his Diſciples, into the Land of</hi> Judea, <hi>and there he tarried with them, and Baptized:</hi> Nay further it appears, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Saviour Baptized thoſe in <hi>Judea,</hi> he repreſented the Solemnity of Baptiſm, as a thing neceſſary to enter Men into that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, to which He invited them; our Saviour not only telling <hi>Nicodemus, John</hi> 13. 5. <hi>That except a Man be born again, he could not ſee the Kingdom of God;</hi> but yet more plainly, <hi>That except he was born again of Water,</hi> v. 5. <hi>and of the Spirit, he could not enter into it.</hi> Agreeable hereto, ſee the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the Apoſtles, <hi>Acts</hi> 8. 36, 38. And as they, (<hi>Philip</hi> and the <hi>Eunuch</hi>) went on their Way, they came to a certain Water, and the Eunuch ſaid, <hi>See, here is Water, what doth hinder me to be Baptized? And he commanded the Chariot to ſtand ſtill; and they went both down into the Water, both</hi> Philip <hi>and the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuch, and he Baptized him:</hi> And as deep a
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:95614:15"/>
Penitent as <hi>Paul</hi> was, (who, no doubt but he was as much, or more, endued with the Holy Spirit, than any <hi>Quaker</hi> in the World) yet <hi>Ananias, Acts</hi> 22. 16. bid him <hi>ariſe and be Baptized, and waſh away thy Sins:</hi> I ſay, no one can pretend to a more ſincere and truer Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, than this Penitent; yet you ſee that inward Baptiſm, as the Quakers call it, was not ſufficient, but to that muſt be added, the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Baptiſm, or waſhing by Water, for the Remiſſion of his Sins; <hi>Ariſe and be Baptized, and waſh away thy Sins;</hi> nay further, and which is more expreſs and plain, ſee <hi>Acts</hi> 10<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 44. whilſt <hi>Peter</hi> was preaching to <hi>Cornelius</hi> and others, we read, that the Holy Ghoſt fell on all them which heard the Word, whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid, Ver. 47. <hi>Can any Man for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid Water, that theſe ſhould not be Baptized, which have received the Holy Ghoſt as well as we? And he commanded them to be Baptized,</hi> Ver. 48. Note, They had that which the Quakers call the inward Baptiſm, yet that was not ſufficient; no; it was but a neceſſary Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification for the reception of the outward Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm by Water: For after it appeared that they had received the Holy Ghoſt, nothing then could hinder them from receiving the outward Baptiſm: <hi>Can any Man forbid Water?</hi> &amp;c. For further proof and ſatisfaction, I refer the Reader to that Excellent Piece of <hi>Water Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm,</hi> writ by that Worthy and Ingenious Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of <hi>The Snake in the Graſs,</hi> &amp;c. Printed 1697. And that they do diſown and reject this
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:95614:16"/>
outward Baptiſm by Water, ſee <hi>Parnel</hi>'s <hi>Shield of Truth,</hi> p. 12. where he ſays, <hi>We</hi> (the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers) <hi>are Accuſed to deny the Baptiſm.</hi> He anſwers, <hi>The Baptiſm we own, which is the Baptiſm of Chriſt, with the Holy Ghoſt, and with Fire, but we deny all other</hi>—See <hi>Will. Penn</hi> his <hi>Reaſon againſt Raiſing,</hi> p. 108, 109. <hi>I affirm,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that Circumciſion is as much in force as Water Baptiſm, and the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal Lamb as the Bread and Wine; for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing of them would have been a Judaizing of the Evangelical Worſhip; to aſſert their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, would be, as much as in ſuch lies, to plack up the Goſpel or Spiritual Worſhip, by the Roots. Hence that Appellation, Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Chriſt, I do ren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nce as unſcri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ral and unevangelical, and can teſtifie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the ſame Spirit by which</hi> Paul <hi>renounced Circumciſion, that they are to be rejected, as not now requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</hi> Note, How this deluded, or rather de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning Man, Patronize his Notorious Falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods to the ſame Spirit that St. <hi>Paul</hi> had, which was the Spirit of Chriſt: Now what is this but Blaſpheming the Holy Spirit? See further <hi>Smith</hi>'s <hi>Primer,</hi> p. 36. it is there af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, that our Baptiſm <hi>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe from the Popes invention—and that it had its Inſtitution from the Pope, and was never ſo ordained of Chriſt;</hi> and their Famous Teacher, <hi>Ed. Burr.</hi> p. 190, 191. tells you, <hi>To ſay that ſprinkling Infants with Water—is Baptiſm into the Faith of Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> this is the Doctrine of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil.</hi> Good God! Tho' theſe poor deluded
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:95614:16"/>
Wretches will not own this Divine and Sacred Inſtitution, that is, Baptiſm by Water, as the one Baptiſm, yet it behoveth them not thus to Calumniate, Vilifie and Abuſe it: I ſhall ſay to theſe, as well as to ſome others, that look upon it to be but an Arbitrary Ceremony, (which I hope they will ſeriouſly lay to Heart) as <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Syrian</hi> did, <hi>What means this waſhing ſeven times in</hi> Jordan? What Vertue can there be in that poor Flement to do away Sins, and to work upon our Souls? I ſay I ſhall ſay, as <hi>Naaman</hi>'s Servants ſaid, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 5. 13. <hi>If Chriſt had bid thee do ſome great thing, couldſt thou not have done it? How much ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then when he ſaith to thee, waſh and be clean.</hi> As neceſſary as the Waters of <hi>Jordan</hi> were to the cleanſing of <hi>Naaman,</hi> ſo neceſſary are the Waters of Baptiſm to the cleanſing of our Souls. None ſure dare ſay, That God could not have cleanſed <hi>Naaman</hi> otherwiſe; but God having by his Prophet appointed the Means, if <hi>Naaman</hi> had neglected it, he had not otherwiſe been Cured; how much more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> when God has appointed the Means of Baptiſm by his Son, if we neglect it, ſhall we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Saved without it? Again, when the Blind Man in the Goſpel, <hi>John</hi> 9. 7. was command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to go and waſh in the Pool of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> which is by interpretation, ſent, and then ſhalt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered; no Man ſure, but an Infidel, will here be inquiſitive and curious, Firſt, In ſearching out the reaſon of this, why upon ſo waſhing, he ſhould be recovered of his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:95614:17"/>
but would ſet his Reaſon aſide, and cheerfully ſubmit to the Preſcription; not at all doubting, but the Means ſo uſed, however little ſhew of Reaſon they carry along with them, will fully anſwer the End deſigned: If God gave a Miraculous Vertue to the Waters of <hi>Jordan, Siloam</hi> and <hi>Betheſda,</hi> for healing of the Fleſh, we cannot doubt, but that the ſame Spirit can and will ſanctifie the Waters of Baptiſm, to the Myſtical waſhing away of Sin, eſpecially having the poſitive Inſtitution and Promiſe of Chriſt. <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 38.—<hi>Repent and be Baptized, every one of you, in the Name of Jeſus Chriſt, for the Remiſſion of Sins, and ye ſhall receive the Gift of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> How dare then any People, or Society of Men, ſlight or reject it! <hi>He that deſpiſed</hi> Moſes's <hi>Law died without Mercy, of how much ſorer Puniſhment ſuppoſe ye, ſhall he be thought worthy, who have trodden under foot the Inſtitution of the Son of God, and count it an indifferent, or an Unholy thing;</hi> doing deſpight to it, inventing contemptible Names for it, and even ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Adminiſtration of it? Whether ſuch ought to be called Chriſtians, I leave the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byaſs'd Reader to judge, and ſo proceed to the next Queſtion, p. 8.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Do you believe or own the Lord's Supper, either as a Sign of the Love that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ought to have among themſelves, or as a Seal of the Saints Communion, and Commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Chriſt's Death for us, or as Figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:95614:17"/>
               <hi>of Chriſt's Body and Blood, Spiritually re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd by Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Supper of the Lord we Own, and renderly Conſider in a Twofold Senſe: 1. In the Figure. 2. In the Subſtance. 1. That our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, at his Supper, with his Diſciples, did eat the Paſſover (which was for the Fulfilling and Conſummation of the Feaſts under the Law) ſee <hi>Luk.</hi> 22. And at this Supper he did Take and Miniſter Bread, and the Cup, to his Diſciples, (for there was no Tranſubſtantiation) ſaying, <hi>This do in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of me:</hi> And ſaid the Apoſtle, <hi>As <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt as ye ſhall eat this Bread, and drink this Cup, ye ſhew the Lord's Death till he come,</hi> 1 Cor. 11. After this they did more clearly know his coming, and Chriſt after the Spirit: Jeſus Chriſt in them, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 5. and 5. 16. 2. And Chriſt ſaid to his Diſciples, <hi>I will not drink henceforth of this Fruit of the Vine, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Day I drink it new with you in my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Kingdom.</hi> Matth. 26. 29. And likewiſe of the Bread, <hi>I will not any more eat thereof, until it be fulfilled in the Kingdom of God,</hi> Luk. 22. 16. And he further ſaid, <hi>I appoint unto you a Kingdom, as my Father hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ointed to me, that ye may eat and drink at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y Table in my Kingdom,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Luk.</hi> 22. 29, 30. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n theſe things we believe he ſpoke Myſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and that every Member of his Spiritual Church, doth daily Spiritually partake of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is Body and Blood by Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:95614:18"/>OBSERVATION.</p>
            <p>The Reader may here diſcern, how by their deceivable Words, and manifold Corruptions of the Scriptures, theſe Horrid Impoſtors ſet themſelves at work, to Evade and make Null the Holy Ordinance of the Lord's Supper, as Inſtituted and Adminiſtred in Bread and Wine, which they deny to be now a ſtanding Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance in the Church of Chriſt, and to be pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctic'd by Chriſtians. The Supper of the Lord they own, but how? Not as now to be conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued and preached; for the breaking of Bread, and drinking of Wine, which we are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to do in remembrance of our Saviour's Body broken, and Blood ſhed for us, was but a Temporary Command, and was to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued no longer than till he came again, <hi>As oft as ye ſhall eat this Bread and drink this Cup, ye ſhew the Lord's Death till he come,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. <hi>v.</hi> 26. but, ſay they, Chriſt is come already in them; <hi>Ergo,</hi> this Ordinance is not to be continued, <hi>p.</hi> 9. <hi>After this they did more clearly know his coming, and Chriſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Spirit, Jeſus Chriſt in them.</hi> They in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret this paſſage of Scripture; not of Chriſt's Outward and Perſonal coming at the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, which (as <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Philetus,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 18.) they ſay is paſt already; but of that which is inwardly performed by the Spiritual Reſurrection of Chriſt, or the Light in their Hearts: And they ſay, that the Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the Lord's Supper was only to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:95614:18"/>
till that inward Coming or Forming of Chriſt in their Hearts; which they have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, (as they blindly preſume) therefore they throw off the outward Supper. But I would ask them, Was not Chriſt formed in the Hearts of the Apoſtles, to whom Chriſt gave his Holy Supper, as much as in the Hearts of any of the beſt Quakers now in the World? Was he not come Spiritually to <hi>Paul,</hi> after his Converſion? And before his Command above Quoted, of continuing the practice of the Lord's Supper till his coming? See <hi>A Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of Water-Baptiſm,</hi> by the <hi>Author of the Snake,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 48. As alſo the Anſwer to <hi>Will. Penn</hi>'s <hi>Key,</hi> p. 93, 94, 95, 96. And did not the Apoſtles, and the Primitive Chriſtians, partake of this Ordinance, even after the Holy Spirit, that Chriſt promiſed to ſend, was come? (which they call the Second coming of Chriſt.) That they did ſo, appears from <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 42, 46. <hi>And they continued ſtedfaſtly in the Apoſtles Doctrine and Fellowſhip, and in breaking of Bread, and in Prayers.—And they continuing daily with one aecord in the Temple, and breaking Bread.</hi> Acts 20. 7. <hi>And the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples came together to break Bread.</hi> And that the Second coming of Chriſt (ſo called by them) is not that coming here meant, is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther evident, in that St. <hi>Paul</hi> and the Primitive Chriſtians did not believe the giving forth of the Spirit, to be the Second coming of Chriſt; becauſe it is plain they Believed and Expected him to come in a Perſonal, Glorious, and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:95614:19"/>
manner, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 20. <hi>We look for the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, who ſhall change our Vile Bodies, and make them like his own Glorious Body:</hi> That being one thing which will be done at that which we call Chriſt's Second coming: And this his Second Perſonal coming, St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and and the Chriſtians, did look for; becauſe they were told, <hi>Acts</hi> 1. 11. <hi>That the ſame Jeſus ſhould ſo come in like manner</hi> (viſible in his Body of Fleſh and Bones) <hi>as ye have ſeen him go in Heaven;</hi> and as Chriſt himſelf ſhewed his Diſciples, <hi>Matt.</hi> 24. that his coming ſhould be Glorious and Viſible, and St. <hi>John</hi> in <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. 7. ſaith long after, the Spirit and Comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was come: <hi>Behold he cometh, every Eye ſhall ſee him, and they that Pierced him ſhall Mourn.</hi> 1 Theſſ. 4. 6. <hi>For the Lord himſelf ſhall deſcend from Heaven with a ſhout, with the noiſe of the Arch-Angel, and the Trump of God,</hi> &amp;c.—This may ſuffice, not only to clear theſe Texts of their corrupt Perverſions; but alſo to Confirm and Satisfie the Reader of the Continuance or Perpetuity of this Sacred Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of the Lord's Supper, in his Church, till his coming again in his Perſon to Judge the World. And as to thoſe other Texts, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 15, 16, 17. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. <hi>Prov.</hi> 9. 4, 5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Jo.</hi> 6. <hi>Pag.</hi> 10. not to mention that of St. <hi>Matth.</hi> 26. v. 29. <hi>Luk.</hi> 22. 16. 23. 30. in their Ninth <hi>Pag.</hi> which they offer to the View of the World, I cannot diſcern or imagine to what end and purpoſe this is done, unleſs it be to amuſe the Reader, abuſe the Scriptures,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:95614:19"/>
or Confute themſelves. I make no doubt but all good Chriſtians own Chriſt to be the Bread of Life, and have Spiritual Communion with him in his Holy Ordinances, which Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion I dare affirm, they cannot have, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever bold pretences they make, who do not obey Chriſt in theſe his Holy Inſtitutions, but ſlight, vilifie and contemn the ſame; and that the Quakers do ſo, ſee <hi>Parnell</hi>'s <hi>Shield of the Truth,</hi> written from the Mouth of the Lord, as the Title Page ſhews, <hi>p.</hi> 13. <hi>We are accuſed,</hi> ſays he, <hi>to deny the Supper of the Lord:</hi> He anſwers, <hi>The Supper of the Lord we own, which is the Body and Blood of Chriſt (that is conſidered Spiritually)—for Saints are Spiritual, and their Communion is Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and Eternal:—And here all Drunkards are ſhut out, and all Liars, Adulterers, Proud, Covetous,</hi> &amp;c.—<hi>And are without, feeding up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Husk, and ſhadow, which is Carnal and Natural, and only feed the Outward Carnal Body, and goeth into the Belly, and ſo paſſeth out,</hi> &amp;c.—<hi>And ſo likewiſe the Cup which they drink, and ſo the Communion and Fellowſhip of the World paſſeth away, but this is no nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Soul:—And here is no Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but Natural, Outward, and Carnal:—Full of filthineſs and uncleanneſs, which is the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Devils, eating and drinking their own Damnation, not diſcerning the Lord's Body, which is Spiritual, which the Natural Man diſcerns not: And here ſtands the World's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion and Fellowſhip, which is Carnal,</hi> p. 14.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:95614:20"/>
               <hi>And here they are without, feeding upon the Husk and Shadow without.</hi> See <hi>Smith</hi>'s <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> p. 36, 37. ſays the Child, <hi>I would know, Father, how it is concerning thoſe things called Ordinances, as Baptiſm, and Bread, and Wine, which are much uſed in their Worſhip.</hi> The Father anſwers, <hi>Why, Child, as to thoſe things, they roſe from the Pope's Invention, who had Power in the Night of Apoſtacy, and hath ſet up his Devices, which are yet continued in</hi> England, <hi>tho' he ſeemingly is denied, and the whole Practice of thoſe things, as they uſe them, bad their Inſtitution by the Pope, and were never ſo ordained of Chriſt: Neither did He Ordain Bread and Wine to be ſo Uſed and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Geo. Fox,</hi> in his <hi>News coming up out out of the North,</hi> &amp;c. p. 4. <hi>Your Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm and Sacrament, as you call it, and all your Ordinances, and Churches, and Teachings, it is</hi> Cain'<hi>s Sacrifice:</hi> And p. 14. <hi>Their Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, as they call it, is Carnal:—Their Communion, Bread and Wine, it is the Table of Devils, and Cup of Devils.</hi> And <hi>W. Penn</hi> in his <hi>Reaſon againſt Railing,</hi> &amp;c. p. 108. <hi>I affirm</hi> (ſays he) <hi>that the Paſchal Lamb is as much in force as Bread and Wine.</hi> And p. 109. <hi>And we can teſtifie from the ſame Spirit, by which</hi> Paul <hi>Renounced Circumciſion, that it is to be Rejected, as not now Required.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Do you believe and own the Holy Scriptures, contained in the Books of the Old and New Teſtament, to be given by Divine In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration,</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:95614:20"/>
               <hi>and to contain all Matters of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Teſtimony,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>neceſſary to be belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and practiſed, in order to Salvation, and Peace with God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes, we do, and by the Aſſiſtance of the Grace of God, which gives the true Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the Mind of God, and M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ning of Holy Scripture; we always deſire to live in the Faith, Knowledge and Practice of them, in all things appertaining to Life and Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Holy Scripture being given by Divine In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration, is Profitable for Doctrine, Correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Inſtruction, that the Man of God may he perfect, thoroughly furniſhed unto every good Work, able to make the Man of God wiſe unto Salvation, thro' Faith in Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p>OBSERVATION.</p>
            <p>Here is, like unto the reſt, a Plauſible Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion; but whether Sincere or not, I leave to the World to judge, when they ſhall have read and conſidered theſe following Quotations. See <hi>John Whitehead</hi> and <hi>Rob. Ruckhill</hi> their <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers Refuge,</hi> p. 17. <hi>Whether the firſt Penman of the Scriptures was</hi> Moſes <hi>or</hi> Hermes? <hi>Or whether both theſe are not one? Or whether there are not many Words contained in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, which were not ſpoken by the Inſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Holy Spirit? Whether ſome Words were not ſpoken by the Grand Impoſtor; ſome by wicked Men; ſome by wiſe Men, ill applied; ſome by good Men, ill expreſſed; ſome by falſe Prophets, and yet true<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſome by true Prophets,</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:95614:21"/>
               <hi>and yet falſe?</hi> &amp;c.—<hi>Sam. Fiſher</hi> in his Appen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dix, p. 752. Printed 1679. has theſe Words, ſpeaking of the Text of Scripture; <hi>Which Tranſcriptions and Tranſlations, were they never ſo certain and entirely anſwering to the firſt Original Copies, yet are not capable to be</hi> (to all Men) <hi>any other than a</hi> Lesbian <hi>Rule, or Noſe of Wax:</hi> (This worthy Author in his Works has the Teſtimony of <hi>Luke Howard, Hallelujah Fiſher,</hi> and <hi>Will. Penn</hi>) and <hi>Lawſon</hi>'s <hi>Untaught Teacher,</hi> p. 2. <hi>To ſay the Word of Truth is called the Scripture, or that the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture is the Word of Truth, is a Lie;</hi> and <hi>Sam. Fiſher,</hi> p. 460. <hi>The Scriptures not the Saints Rule, but the Spirit;</hi> and <hi>Sword of the Lord drawn,</hi> p. 1, 2. <hi>The Scriptures are not the Saints Rule of knowing God, and living unto him:</hi> And <hi>Edw. Barrough,</hi> p. 47. <hi>No Command in Scripture was any further binding, than as we are convinced of the Lawfulneſs thereof by the Light within:</hi> For ſays he, <hi>That is no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand from God to me, what he commands to another; neither did any of the Saints, which we read of in Scripture, act by the Command which was to another, not having the Command to themſelves.</hi> See <hi>G. Fox</hi>'s <hi>Gr. Myſt.</hi> p. 246. <hi>The Scriptures are not the Word of God;</hi> yet he ſays of his own Writings, p. 225. <hi>To you all this is the Word of the Lord.</hi> Nay, <hi>James Nayler</hi> in his Anſwer to the <hi>Jews,</hi> p. 22, 25. <hi>It's Blaſphemy for any to ſay the Letter is the Word of God; it is the Devil that contends for the Scriptures to be the Word of God.</hi> This
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:95614:21"/>
               <hi>Will. Penn</hi> at a venture vindicates, tho' he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes he never ſaw the Book, out of which it was quored; ſee his Pamphlet, Entituled, <hi>A Brief Anſwer to a Falſe and Fooliſh Libel, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, The</hi> Quakers <hi>Opinions,</hi> p. 15. Printed 1678. The Queſtion being asked the <hi>Quakers,</hi> ſee <hi>Will. Penn</hi> and <hi>G. Whitehead</hi> their <hi>Serious Apology,</hi> p. 49. <hi>Do you eſteem your Speakings to be of as great Authority as any Chapter in the Bible?</hi> The Anſwer is in theſe Words, <hi>That which is ſpoken by the Spirit of Truth in any, is of as great Authority as the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures and Chapters are, and greater.</hi> See <hi>Lawſon</hi>'s <hi>Threefold Eſtate of Antichriſt,</hi> p. 9. <hi>The Scripture is Duſt and Death—Beaſtly Wares,</hi> &amp;c. And for a Concluſion of this Head, ſee <hi>G. Fox</hi>'s <hi>News out of the North,</hi> p. 14. <hi>Your Original is Carnal, Hebrew, Greek and Latin, and your Word is Carnal, the Letter—Their Original is Duſt, which is the Letter, which is Death, and their Goſpel is but Duſt,</hi> Matthew, Mark, Luke <hi>and</hi> John, <hi>which is the Letter.</hi> Again, ſee <hi>Will. Bayley</hi>'s Works, <hi>p.</hi> 195. <hi>viz. The Scriptures in</hi> NO SENSE <hi>can properly be called the Word of God,</hi> &amp;c. yet with Reſpect to their own Scriptures, (I mean what is given forth by their Light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in) is in ſome Senſe the Word of God, elſe why did <hi>G. Fox</hi> in his <hi>Several Papers, given forth for the ſpreading of Truth,</hi> (and in which Book he alſo calls the Scriptures <hi>Duſt, Death, and Serpents Food,</hi> p. 3, 4, 45, 46.) thus writes? p. 62. <hi>To you all, this is the Word</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:95614:22"/>
               <hi>of the Lord; I charge you in the Preſence of the Lord God, to ſend this</hi> (Book) <hi>among Friends and Brethren every where, to be</hi> READ <hi>in</hi> ALL <hi>Meetings to you all;</hi> THIS IS THE WORD OF GOD. Now if <hi>Fox</hi> did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve this Book of his to be in NO SENSE the Word of God, why did he charge his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples to ſend it up and down as THE WORD OF GOD, to charge and command them to read it as THE WORD OF GOD in SOME SENCE, at leaſt; and that in all their MEET<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>INGS, whilſt they ſay, as above noted, the Scriptures are not the Word of God: No, not in ANY SENCE? And therefore as Mr. <hi>Bugg</hi> has well obſerved, that in all the time of his being a <hi>Quaker,</hi> which was 25 Years, they never Read one Chapter in the Bible, or one of the Epiſtles of the Holy Apoſtles in ANY ONE of their Meetings; nor can they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove what he ſays, in THAT, as well as in OTHER things.</p>
            <p>Now, whether they have ſuch a great E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem and Veneration for the Holy Scriptures, valuing and preferring them before all other Books extant in the World, as in their new Creeds they tell us, and as they made frequent Outcries at <hi>Weſt-Dereham</hi> Conference before Thouſands, let the <hi>Reader</hi> judge.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Do you believe the Doctrine of the Reſurrection from the Dead, and of Eternal Judgment, and the Immortality of the Soul?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:95614:22"/>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> We ſincerely believe and confeſs the Doctrine of the Reſurrection from the Dead, and of Eternal Judgment, according to Holy Scripture, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 2.</p>
            <p>That God will raiſe the Dead, and judge the World in Righteouſneſs by His Son Jeſus Chriſt, in the Day appointed, even in the great Day of Judgment, and that Harveſt, which is the end of the World.</p>
            <p>Tho' the Soul of Man, tho' Created, is Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal, and never dies, even as theſe Doctrines are more fully teſtified in Holy Scripture by Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt and His Apoſtles: 1<hi>ſt,</hi> For the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Reſurrection, ſee <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. 43. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 15.</p>
            <p>OBSERVATION.</p>
            <p>The Anſwer is, VVe ſincerely believe and confeſs the Doctrine of the Reſurrection from the Dead—according to Holy Scripture, that is according to their Senſe and Interpretation of Holy Scripture, which is no ways agreeable to the Senſe and Interpretation of any Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Chriſtians. To that end, ſee <hi>Will<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Penn</hi>'s <hi>Reaſon againſt Railing,</hi> p. 134. it is objected, That the IT in the Text, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. be not the ſame Body; how can that be called a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection? For that ſuppoſeth the ſame. To which <hi>Penn</hi> anſwers, <hi>If a thing can yet be the ſame, and notwithſtanding changed, for Shame let us never make ſo much ſtir againſt the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Tranſubſtantiation; for the Abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of that is rather outdone, than equalled by</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:95614:23"/>
               <hi>this Carnal Reſurrection.</hi> Ibid. <hi>p.</hi> 138. It was objected by his Opponent, <hi>That the Joys of Heaven would be imperfect, if the Bodies did not Riſe.</hi> He Anſwers, <hi>Is the Joy of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients, now in Glory, imperfect? Or are they in Heaven, but by halves, if it be ſo unequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, that the Body which hath Suffered ſhould not partoke of the Joys Caeleſtial? Is it not in meaſure unequal, that the Soul ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded ſo long before the Body?—But why muſt the felicity of the Soul depend upon that of the Body? Is it not to make the Soul a kind of Widow, and ſo in a ſtate of Mourning and Diſconſolateneſs, to be without its beloved Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy? Which State is but a better ſort of Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>—In ſhort, if the compleat Happineſs of the Soul reſts in a Re-union to a Carnal Body, for ſuch it is Sown, then never cry out upon the</hi> Turks Alcoran; <hi>for ſuch a Heaven, and the Joys of it, ſuit admirably well with ſuch a Reſurrection.</hi> See his <hi>Invalidity of</hi> John F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do'<hi>s Vindication,</hi> p. 369, 370. <hi>I do utterly deny, that this Text</hi> (1 Cor. 15. 44.) <hi>is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in the Reſurrection of Man's Carnal Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy at all,—but the two States of Men under the Firſt and Second</hi> Adam: <hi>Men are Sown into the World Natural, ſo are they the Sons of the Firſt</hi> Adam; <hi>but they are Raiſed Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually, thro' him who is the Reſurrection and the Life, and ſo are they the Sons of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond</hi> Adam,—<hi>who came to Raiſe up the Sons of the Firſt</hi> Adam <hi>from their Dead, to his Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, their Natural to his Spiritual Eſtate.</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:95614:23"/>
               <hi>But perhaps it will be objected, that the</hi> 47 verſ. <hi>The Firſt Man is of the Earth, Earthly; and part of the</hi> 49 verſ. <hi>We that alſo bear the Image of the Heavenly, ſeem to imply a Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily Reſurrection; but let the whole Verſe be conſidered, and we ſhall find no ſuch thing,</hi> &amp;c.—See <hi>Tho Ellwood</hi> in his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to <hi>G. Keith</hi>'s firſt <hi>Narrative</hi> p. 149. Printed 1696. <q>In 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 37. he makes the Apoſtle thus ſpeak, The Body that ſhall ariſe, is not the ſame Carnal Body that Dies, and is put into the Grave: No; the Body that is put into the Grave (or is Sown) is a Natural Body; but the Body that is Raiſed is a Spiritual Body: It is Sown a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Body, it is Raiſed a Spiritual Body. <hi>Ver.</hi> 44. And that none might think this Spiritual Body was the ſame with the Natural Body, he adds, There is a Natural Body, and there is a Spiritual Body. He does not ſay, the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural is made a Spiritual Body, or the Natural Body and the Spiritual Body is but one and the ſame Body: But he ſets them in Oppoſition, as two diſtinct Bodies, and that none might think this Spiritual Bodies was the ſame, he adds, there is a Natural Body, and there is a Spiritual Body.</q> Further, ſee <hi>Rich. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bberthorn</hi>'s Collections, <hi>p.</hi> 119. he there tells his Opponent, <q>That he Lies concerning the Saints on Earth,</q> ſaying, <q>The Saints in Heaven hoped for the perfection of their Bodies at the Reſurrection, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>—And his Envy hath reached to Heaven, to prove that the Saints in Heaven are not perfect, but wait for the Redemption of their Bodies; which now if People mind the Scriptures, there is no ſuch Doctrine in it, as the Saints in Heaven have not receiv'd the Redemption of their Bodies.</q> And again, <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 121. <q>Theſe are they (<hi>viz.</hi> the World's People, or Truth's Enemies) that ſay, that the Saints Glorified in Heaven, do yet hope for the Reſurrection of their Bodies, and ſo not come to the end of their hope, tho' in Heaven.</q> But whatever whimſical Notions they are poſſeſſed with, and whatever falſe Gloſſes they put upon Scripture, yet I hope all Good and Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Chriſtians will readily believe and ſay with <hi>Job</hi> c. 19. v. 25, 26, 27. <hi>I know that my Redeemer liveth, and that he ſhall ſtand at the latter Day upon the Earth, and altho' after my Skin, Worms deſtroy my Body, yet in my Fleſh ſhall I ſee God: Whom I ſhall ſee for my ſelf, and not another: Mine Eyes ſhall behold him, tho' my Reins be conſumed within me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:95614:24"/>We (ſay the <hi>Quakers</hi>) ſincerely Believe, That God will Judge the World in Righteouſneſs by his Son Jeſus Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in the Day appointed, even in the Great Day of Judgment, and that Harveſt, which is the End of the World.</p>
            <p>Obſerve their ſincerity; to that end, ſee <hi>G. Whitehead's Light and Life,</hi> p. 41. <hi>What is that Glory of the Father, in which his Coming is? Is it viſible to the Carnal Eye? And when was that coming to be? Is it now to be looked for outwardly?—We do acknowledge the ſeveral Comings of Chriſt according to the Scriptures, both that in the Fleſh, and that in the Spirit;—but Three Comings of Chriſt,</hi> [not only that in the Fleſh at <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> and that in the Spirit, but alſo another Coming in the Fleſh, yet to be expected] <hi>we do not read of, Vid.</hi> his <hi>Nature of Chriſtianity,</hi> p. 29. <hi>Doſt thou look for Chriſt, as the Son of</hi> Mary, <hi>to appear outwardly, in a bodily Exiſtence, to ſave thee—if thou doſt, thou maiſt look until thy Eyes drop out, before thou wilt ſee ſuch an Appearance of him,</hi> &amp;c. To this purpoſe, ſee <hi>Dewsbury</hi>'s <hi>Diſcovery of Man's Return,</hi> written from the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Lord, p. 7. Printed 1654, where he quotes <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. 12, 13. <hi>I ſaw the Dead, ſmall and great, ſtand before God; and the Books were opened, and another Book was opened, which is the Book of Life; and the Dead were judged out of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe things, which were written in the Books, according to their Works, and the Sea gave up the Dead which were in it; and Death and Hell delivered up the Dead which were in them; and they were judged every Man according to their Works.</hi> And, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 10. <hi>We muſt all appear before the Judgment-ſeat of Chriſt, that every one may receive the things done in the B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Obſerve here his groſs Perverſion, he applying all this to the Light within, and the Judgment within; ſo that the outward Judgment at the Laſt Day, which is here ſo plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſcribed, is not by him profeſſed as a thing to be expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: His words are theſe, <q>Every one ariſe out of your Earthly Wiſdom, and mind the Light in thy Conſcience, and wait on the Power of the Lord in it, and it will bring thee to Judgment before the Throne of the Lamb, (<hi>viz. within thee</hi>) where the Righteous Law will be opened in thy Heart, that will cry through thy Earthly Heart for Righteouſneſs and Judgment, and the Book will be open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed IN THEE, where thou ſhalt ſee all written that thou haſt done in the Body, and ſhalt give an account for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry idle word, (i. e. <hi>to the Light within</hi>) and receive thy
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:95614:24"/>
Reward for what thou haſt done, and thy Reward is Wrath and Condemnation, which will paſs upon thee from the preſence of the Lamb, (<hi>within thee</hi>) for thy Diſobedience, and breaking of the Righteous Law.</q> And thus according to Scripture, (<hi>i. e.</hi> according to their Interpretation of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture) do they believe the Doctrine of Eternal Judgment, <hi>viz.</hi> the Judgment of the Heart or Conſcience, accuſing or excuſing them.</p>
            <p>We Believe, (ſay the <hi>Quakers)</hi> That the Soul of Man, tho Created, is Immortal, and never dies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>OBSERVATION.</p>
            <p>They ſeem here to Confeſs and Believe, That the Soul is a Created Being, and indeed to it is, as alſo Immortal. But hear what <hi>G. Fox</hi> ſays in his <hi>Gr. Myſt.</hi> p. 100. where he makes the Soul to be part of God: <hi>Is not this that cometh out from God, which is in God's Hand, part of God?—And is not that which came out from God, which God hath in his Hand, taken up into God again, which Chriſt the Power of God is the Biſhop of, is not this of God's Being?</hi> lb. p. 91. <hi>Chriſt the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of their Souls—brings the Soul up into God, from whence it came, whereby they come to be one Soul: If it be of God's Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, it cannot be a Creature.</hi> And that it is not a Creature, ſee further <hi>G. Fox</hi>'s <hi>Myſt.</hi> p. 29. One <hi>Magnus Byne</hi> had ſaid, The Soul is not Infinite in it ſelf, but it is a Creature; and ſaith <hi>R. Baxter,</hi> It is a Spiritual Subſtance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To which he anſwers, <hi>Now conſider what a Condition theſe called Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters are in: They ſay, That which is a Spiritual Subſtance, is not Infinite in it ſelf, but a Creature: That which come out from the Creator, and is in the Hend of the Creator, which brings it up and to the Creator again, that is Infinite in it ſelf.</hi> And, p. 90. <hi>Is not the Soul without beginning, coming from God, returning into God again, who hath it in his Hand.—And Chriſt the Power of God, the Biſhip of the Soul, which brings it up into God, which came out from him; hath this a begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning or ending? And is not this Infinite in it ſelf?</hi> A Infinite in it ſelf, it muſt be God, nothing being Infinite in it ſelf but God; conſequently the Soul is then no Creature, or Created Being. Theſe Paſſages are vindicated by <hi>W. Penn<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> in his Tract, Entituled, <hi>A Brief Anſwer to a Falſe and Foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Libel, &amp;c.</hi> p. 16. after a very Brief Vindication, he thus concludes, <hi>Where is the Hereſie of this?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:95614:25"/>For a Concluſion; if the <hi>Quakers</hi> be Sincere in this their Profeſſion, if this little Pampalet under Conſideration, as well as many others of the like nature of late diſperſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the World, do really, truly and unfeignedly contain their Faith; it is but then reaſonable to expect that they ſhould, by ſome Publick Act of theirs, Retract, Cenſure and Condemn, all thoſe Tenets or Doctrines which (as I have ſhown) are directly oppoſite and contradictory to theſe New Creeds; THIS INDEED, and NOTHING but THIS, can ſatisfie or convince the World of their Honeſty and Sincerity: But how little of Sincerity there is in theſe Confeſſions, I leave it to the Reader and the World to judge; for they are ſo far from Cenſuring, Condemning, or Diſowning thoſe Books, which contain in them theſe Horrid Blaſphemies, that they tell you, <hi>They have not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viated in any one Paint of Doctrine which they firſt held:</hi> For <hi>Joſeph Wyeth</hi> in his <hi>Primitive Chriſtianity Continued,</hi> p. 6. Printed 1698. thus affirms, <hi>That our Principles are now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o other than what they were when firſt a People:</hi> And in their <hi>Yearly Epiſtle,</hi> Printed 1696<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they ſay, <hi>We cannot but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend unto you the holding up the Holy Teſtimony of Truth, which had made us to be a People, and that in all the Parts of it; for Truth is one, and CHANGES not:</hi> And in a Piece called the <hi>Quakers Cleared,</hi> p. 7. thus they declare, <hi>God is the ſame, his People the ſame, and their Principles the ſame:</hi> And ſays <hi>G. Whitehead</hi> in his <hi>Counterfeit Convert,</hi> Printed 1694. p. 72. <hi>I may ſee cauſe otherwiſe word the Matter, and yet our Intentions be the ſame.</hi> Thus do they ſtifly maintain, That they are not changed in any Point of Doctrine; they do but word the Matter otherwiſe, they mean the ſame with them; only it is convenient now to diſguiſe our Meanings; for at the ſame time, we will ſtand by the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies of our Ancient Friends, as being all given forth by the immediate Dictates of the Holy Ghoſt; to this end they inſerted a Paragraph in the <hi>Poſtman,</hi> Numb. 568. upon occaſion of the late Conference at <hi>Weſt-Dereham</hi> in <hi>Norfolk,</hi> wherein are theſe wards, <hi>The</hi> Quakers <hi>not queſtioning but to acquit their Ancient Friends, and their Writings, from thoſe black Charges, nor being Conſcious of deviating in any ONE POINT of Doctrine, from what they firſt held.</hi> So that as I ſaid at firſt, there is juſt Cauſe to ſuſpect them in all they ſay.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:95614:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
